Tired of searching for subtitles?
Ray generates them instantly: getray.app
Now. this is a musket.
It's a gun. a weapon.
-Gun.
-Weapon.
-Weapon. That's right. Yeah.
Ball. Wad. Powder.
-[imitates explosion] Yeah?
-[imitates explosion] Yeah.
-[mumbles] Mouth?
-Mouth?
-[speaks Hawaiian]
-There was a cape? The red?
Red mouth.
-Weapon.
-Red-mouthed weapon. That's right.
Lion.
[children] Lion.
[John roars]
[children roar in distance]
[sighs]
Barrel. Butt. Trigger.
Cock. Flint.
Frizzen.
Now you're learning.
That's good.
[hammer cocks]
[in Hawaiian] I thought you
would be back in Maui by now.
I did not think I would have
to come to Oʻahu for you.
[grunts]
Oʻahu has not fallen as
easily as we thought.
And you did not come to Oʻahu.
I summoned you.
You are my advisor.
The Maui Chiefs are eager
for further conquest.
They are hopeful to see
the Prophecy fulfilled.
Let us hope we can
be worthy of it.
My Prince.
Your father is waiting for
you with his war party.
What war party?
We can't hold much longer.
There are only a few
strongholds left.
Kahekili acts on the
visions his god shows him.
If we kill Kahekili.
the vision dies with him.
How?
Our spies have poisoned the
food of the King's Council.
They should return shortly.
[bushes rustling]
[warrior gasps]
Your desperation has done this.
old friend.
You are lineage of
the great Kākuhihewa.
Kneel before the Prophesied King
and the last of Oʻahu's
Chiefs will follow.
[breathes heavily]
[captives whimpering. crying]
Wait!
Please. Not my family.
I pledge to you my loyalty.
my King.
[scoffs. sighs]
Loyalty?
[scoffs]
Loyalty.
You chose poison for me.
Now choose it for one of them.
What?
[whimpers]
Please.
Not this.
[Kahekili] Your bloodline
is not worthy to serve in
the Kingdom of Thunder.
Kill them all.
[grunts]
-[shouts in Hawaiian]
-[captive whimpering]
[chief screams]
[captive splutters. chokes]
[children laughing]
[grunts]
[grunting]
[gasps. grunts]
[warrior] Where is he?
He's on the shore.
[warriors] There's Kamehameha!
[warriors laughing]
You've been spending
much of your time here.
You missed another
council meeting.
This is no way to
lead your district.
Here. with my warriors.
we yield results.
At the council. we
yield more talk.
There is news from Kaʻū.
Your uncle's health grows worse.
His time as king
is growing short.
He has asked for you
and your cousin.
[king coughing]
He is here. Father.
Some have questioned
why I keep the relics
of the Paleskin
among the trophies
of conquered Chiefs.
Captain Cook was a great Chief.
He was an ignorant navigator.
surrounded by weak men.
Nothing more.
Stand Kamehameha.
I am on the journey of death.
My time is too short
for formalities.
[coughing]
King Kahekili grows stronger
and will come to our shores.
I fear the gods will deny me
the greatest battle in the
history of our kingdoms.
When I die.
how will you protect Hawaiʻi?
You hold the great God of War.
No king has lost when...
I will call Kahekili to the
blackened earth of Kaʻū.
Here with the great God of War
we will destroy him
and silence the
thunder he worships.
What say you. Kamehameha?
Should the day come you
are no longer with us.
Keōua will be king.
I will follow where he leads.
[grunts]
Keōua is not king today.
Speak your mind.
How would you
protect our kingdom?
I would increase
our food storage.
In the battle of Kamokuhī.
Hawaiʻi forces attacked
a post in Lānaʻi.
With no food.
the warriors were forced to
eat wild roots of kūpala.
bringing a great
sickness of loose bowels.
Hawaiʻi lost. not for
lack of warriors or spears
but lack of food.
Even if we began today
it would take nine months
to have enough storage.
I have already begun.
We have storage huts near every
sacred site in Kohala's district.
[coughing]
I must rest.
[John. in English] "...As they
that went before were affrighted."
"Surely such are the
dwellings of the wicked."
Uh. you said you would
tell me of your travels.
Uh...
A... Ala... Alaska?
Yes. Alaska.
Alaska.
-Hmm.
-It is. um. real?
Oh. it is real.
A land of endless white snow.
Frozen rain.
[Moku] Kaʻahumanu.
Stay. John.
Our lesson for
today is not over.
[in Hawaiian] It is time.
[in English] I ask you to speak
English when John Young is here.
[in Hawaiian] He
is neither warrior
nor Chief
and of no importance to me.
[in English] Go
away. John Young.
The High Priest said you marry
tonight under the moon of Māhealani.
Not yet. please.
[in English] We wait no more.
[crew chattering]
Take a generous pour. gentlemen.
You've earned it.
[friend] Some for Kaʻiana too.
[crew mate] Still don't know why
Captain pulled him from the water.
Sand lovin' devils would
never do that for us.
He saved the captain.
They killed John over there.
Figured you'd care more about that
than your brown-bellied friend.
If it were up to me. we'd go back
and take the island for ourselves.
That's why ain't nothing
left up to you. Marley.
[scoffs] You just an idiot
masquerading as a fool.
Sailing open waters together
does not make us equal.
Don't you forget that. boy.
Your ration.
If you don't want it. sell it
or trade with one of the men.
They have nothing I want.
You spend more time with these
guns than you do with the crew.
I am not crew.
I go home after trade.
They need me there.
Yes.
Your Prophecy.
[scoffs]
As far as I've seen. Kaʻiana. men
of every color do unspeakable things
for their gods and the
prophesies they believe in.
I must go back.
Uh-huh. I guess you'll
get your chance.
Captain says we should reach
Zamboanga in the next day or so.
You'll be heading
home after that.
Is it true in Zamboanga
you can get anything?
For a price.
[panting]
[in Hawaiian] Father!
Why force me to marry now?
King Kalaniʻōpuʻu is near death.
Soon Kamehameha will
face more responsibility.
You continue to
speak of politics
but have yet to tell me
the real reason I am here.
Kamehameha needs you.
[sighs]
I will be one of
many wives to come.
What need does he have of me?
I believe Kamehameha to
be the Prophesied One.
How can this be?
[sighs]
I was Chief to
Kamehameha's father.
I was there the
night he was born.
It was the same night the prophetic
star burned across the sky.
While everyone waited
for a king to rise.
I saw a king born.
[sighs]
But he is hesitant
to accept who he is.
But you
trust in who you are.
I need you to show him
how to do the same.
[breathing heavily]
[rock strikes tree]
I have heard of your
abilities as a warrior.
[in English] How are you?
[in Hawaiian] I heard
you are to marry.
[in English] How are you?
[grunts]
[bell ringing]
[crew chattering]
[captain] Listen up!
To those of you leaving
us once we dock.
I wish you well and
thank you for your work.
For those staying on for the
expedition back to Alaska.
remain close and conduct
yourselves appropriately.
You know. don't get lost
at the bottom of a mug
-or between the legs of some lass.
-[crew laughs]
Prepare the cargo.
The faster we unload. the
faster we all get paid.
That's a King's ransom you're
holding in your hands. Kaʻiana.
Men will trade for this?
Oh. yes.
And nothing better than
grog and a hot bath.
[chuckles]
[chattering]
[friend] I know a place where
the grog and the food are good.
but the women are ugly.
That's just how I like it.
Let's go.
[metal banging]
How may I be of service?
-We trade.
-You would like to buy it?
[Kaʻiana] Need more.
[gunsmith] How many more?
Many.
[gunsmith laughs]
You thought you could just go in there
and buy yourself an army's worth of guns?
[chuckles] Come on.
We can talk about
it over some food.
Hey.
Wait here. I may
be a minute or two.
[drunk] You!
You!
What are you supposed to be?
[burps]
You look like a fucking peacock.
-What is that... [gasps. groans]
-[growling]
[in Hawaiian] You there.
A Chief of Maui here?
You're Hawaiian.
Come.
[groans]
[scoffs. grunts]
[in English] Welcome to the jewel
in Zamboanga's crown of shit.
If you are looking for
trade. I am your woman.
I've been everywhere. so
I can get you anything.
-[hisses]
-[woman gasps]
My name is Waineʻe. but the
Haole can never pronounce it.
So they call me Vai.
Who the hell are you?
[in Hawaiian] I am
Kaʻiana. son of ʻAhuʻula.
ʻAhuʻula?
[in English] How does a chief of
Maui find himself in Zamboanga?
[friend] We was lost.
We got lucky in
finding them islands.
Picked him up along the way.
Your ship is still here?
[friend] For a few more days.
Captain has another expedition planned.
said he'd take Kaʻiana home after that.
But first. we get
red-mouth weapon.
I don't know how you're gonna
get enough guns for an army.
Why do you need guns?
[in Hawaiian] I made a
mistake. I must fix it.
[in English] With guns?
It must have been a big mistake.
[in Spanish] Go!
Go!
Kaʻiana.
[in English] Speak English here.
And change into something that
does not turn too many heads.
I can get your guns.
[in Hawaiian] Why help me?
[in English] Because you
are going to help me.
[Kaʻiana] Mmm.
We have just finished the longest
haul this ship has ever seen.
Right.
Now. I have no love for
these Spanish bastards.
but they pay well... [laughs]
...and they are hungry for
anything that I might bring 'em.
But what kind of deal would I need
from the likes of. you know. you? Yeah?
Kaʻiana needs guns.
Guns?
I couldn't get you
guns if I wanted to.
It's too much trouble with
the officials. you know.
I have friends who
work around them.
Ah.
So smugglers? Right.
So you're looking for a loan.
See...
afraid that's not a business
I entertain. either.
You will be repaid with a
business endeavor men kill for.
[captain] Sandalwood?
[speaks Hawaiian]
[in English] It is so rare
that a trader from Zamboanga can
sell it for five times its value
in both China and Europe.
And our islands have
mountains full of it.
You want to start
a sandalwood trade?
[Vai] We would be partners.
It will make you richer than
you ever thought possible.
[captain] Well. we would
only be one ship. you know.
So how would we compete
against East India?
They do not know where
our small islands lie.
And you will have Kaʻiana to help convince
the chiefs of our home to allow it.
You sell our home?
[speaks Hawaiian]
[in English] No.
The trade would be ours.
The money to benefit our people.
It will work. Kaʻiana.
I have thought about
this for many years.
Yeah. it could work.
You have been gone too long.
[in Hawaiian] You see the
world like the Paleskin.
You should too. Kaʻiana.
[door closes]
[grunts]
[Vai. in English] It was
not always like this here.
This was their home
before the Spanish came.
They took everything.
They will come to our islands.
Turn that into another Zamboanga.
[scoffs]
We will fight them.
With what? Your spear?
That is no match for their guns
and the Pale-man's greed is stronger
than any god or prophesy you fight for.
There has to be another way.
It is only a matter of time before our
waters will be full of foreign ships.
all of which to trade
or to take what we have.
Sandalwood is money. and money
is all the Pale-man respect.
Maybe all you respect. too.
We can control the
future of our people.
But we cannot do it
without you. Kaʻiana.
You are the only chief who knows
what will come to our shores.
Either we control the trade
or we lose everything.
Get your guns and
let us return home.
[person speaking Spanish]
[captive grunting]
[in English] Good
evening. Captain Metcalfe.
[Marley] Captain Metcalfe.
Do I know you?
I'm Marley. a blacksmith
and armorer by trade.
I have crew. Mr. Marley.
I'm not looking
for a job. Captain.
There's a cluster of unmapped
islands deep in the Pacific.
Untouched by the hands
of Christian men.
Whoever takes these islands
can control the pathways of the
Pacific from Alaska to Canton.
Why. we'd be the kings
of our own paradise.
Why bring this to me?
I've seen the Sand
Savage up close.
They are a warrior people with
no fear of musket and cannon.
as of yet.
Few trade-captains would be willing
to do what must be done in order to...
[sighs] ...tame them.
[in Hawaiian] Father.
So you know.
your mother and I did not betroth
you without careful consideration.
You have a duty to your Chief.
You think that I would give my
only daughter away out of duty?
[sighs]
As king.
Kamehameha will
face many unknowns.
The gods have made it
clear to me. Kaʻahumanu.
the person he needs is you.
Then why have the gods
kept their secrets from me?
As a Chief's wife. my first
duty is to bear him a son.
an heir to help
spread his legacy.
The Prophetess saw
nothing for me.
She said the seed of
Kamehameha cannot live in me.
What does that mean?
It means I will never
bear him children.
When he sees there
is no future with me.
he will turn to a wife
that can carry his child.
I am so sorry. Father.
but I will never be
what you hoped for.
Never tell him this.
[chattering]
[speaks indistinctly]
Well. what's your name?
Ah.
Come on. You show me the way.
[person singing in Hawaiian]
[singing continues]
[singing stops]
Greetings to you. the
finest blossom of East Maui.
[singing resumes]
[singing continues]
As his newest wife. you
will share his bed as we do.
Your life will be
in service of his.
Do not fight it. Kaʻahumanu.
Your children will bring the
union of Hawaiʻi with Maui.
It is a blessing.
[in English] What is this?
Hoʻomaukeiki.
The gods ask Kaʻahumanu
to give Kamehameha a son.
To the woman in
the rising flame.
there was a seeking of
the lost. Now it is found.
A mate is found. one to
share the chills of winter.
The sky is changing.
Hākoʻilani. the house
of respite is secured.
Love has made a plea that
you two become united.
Here is a perch. a
heavenly resting place.
You two are now one.
The darkness withdraws.
The east is beginning
to brighten.
For the day is here at last!
The night is kapu until the
light of the day arrives.
You are wedded.
free to each other.
The prayer has taken flight.
The day is here.
The prayer is said.
The kapu is freed.
I pray the gods have
blessed us this night.
Yes. my Chief.
[Marley] You move real easy in the dark
with that nigger skin. don't ya. boy?
What the hell are you
doing here. Marley?
[chuckles]
-I just... Captain asked me to...
-[gun cocks]
Captain never told you nothing.
Yeah.
Well. why don't we wait for him to
come back and we'll see what he said.
[gun cocks]
[grunts]
[grunting. groaning]
He'd be worth more
alive than dead.
[panting]
[Marley] Did ya hear that?
I'm gonna send you
back where you belong.
[grunts. exclaims]
No. No.
No! No...
[panting]
[grunts]
Get out of here.
Watch Online Movies and Series for FREE
www.osdb.link/lm